Sarah Gertrude Knott papers
American Folklife Center, Library of Congress
- Series 8. Publicity and research
  - Publicity for the 2nd National Folk Festival (2/2), June 8, 1935 (Box-folder 12/3)
    A photocopied article titled "Mountain Music Plus," reprinted from Stand By (June 8, 1935 issue), with Knott's handwritten notes. Relocated from box-folder 10/35.
  - "The Return of the Troubadours," by T.H. Alexander, April 1939 (Box-folder 10/36)
    Original pages from the April 1939 issue of The Rotarian. Received at AFC in a folder with the heading: Berea Kentucky Knott and the Re [sic] of... [The Return of the Troubadours]. This folder is in the current folder.
  - "The Plain People," by M.J. Pickering, March 9, 1941 (Box-folder 10/37)
    Clipping from the Washington Post. Received at AFC in a folder with the heading: The Amish People - Pickering. This folder is in the current folder.
  - Proof and photocopied pages for an essay by Rev. Albert Muntsch, 1944 or 1949 (Box-folder 10/38)
    An essay on folklore by Rev. Albert Muntsch, in Notes and Queries; includes handwritten edits. Received at AFC in a folder with the heading: 11th National Folk Festival/Philadelphia, Pennsylvania. This folder is in the current folder.
  - "Spin Your Own Fun," 1950 (Box-folder 10/39)
    Photocopy of an article about the upsurge of folk activities. Received at AFC in a folder with the heading: Spin Your Own Fun - The Country's Gentlemen. This folder is in the current folder.
  - "The Folk Arts," by Paul Green, circa 1953 (Box-folder 11/1)
    Photocopied essay by Paul Green; possibly from the book Dramatic Heritage (circa 1953). Received at AFC in a folder with the heading: The Folk Arts - Green, Paul. This folder is with the current folder.
  - History of the Zuni nation (1/2), August 10, 1954 (Box-folder 11/2)
    A newspaper section on the history of the Zuni nation from the time of Christianity; this has been relocated to box-folder 12/11. Received at AFC in a folder with the heading: Ceremonial edition newspaper/Indians - Zuni and Navajo. This folder is with the current folder.
  - History of the Zuni nation (2/2), August 10, 1954 (Box-folder 12/11)
    Section of a newspaper on the history of the Zuni nation, from the time of Christianity. Relocated from box-folder 11/2.
  - "Folksingers and Folksongs in America," circa early-mid 1960s (Box-folder 11/3)
    Photocopy of a folder and a photocopied selection of pages from the Ray Lawless book, Folksingers and Folksongs in America (1960 or 1965 edition). Received at AFC in a folder with the heading: Publicity by Ray Lawless SGK.
  - "Round Dancing Isn't 'Square,'" 1966, 1978 (Box-folder 11/4)
    Newspaper clipping from Empire (a magazine; published as part of the Denver Post, January 30, 1966) on round dancing. Received at AFC in a folder with the heading: Southern Folklore Newsletter/Memphis, Tennessee.
  - "Tune for 'Baldy Green,'" by Ben Gray Lumpkin, March 1970 (Box-folder 11/5)
    Offprint from Southern Folklore Quarterly, v. 34, no. 1. Received at AFC in a folder with the heading: "Baldy Green" by Ben Gray Lumpkin. This folder is with the current folder.
  - "The National Folk Festival Association," by Archie Green, 1935 and possibly 1975 (Box-folder 11/6)
    A photocopy of an article by Archie Green, published in Commercial Music Graphics, no. 32, and a photocopy of the program for the 2nd National Folk Festival.
  - "Buell Kazee," by Loyal Jones, after 1976 (Box-folder 11/7)
    A published essay, removed from a magazine. Kazee died in 1976. Received at AFC in a folder with the heading: Kazee, Buell by Jones, Loyal.
  - "Recent Visitor Here, Champion of American Folk Tradition," December 6, 1978 (Box-folder 11/8)
    Photocopy of an article about Sarah Gertrude Knott's visit to Prestonburg, Kentucky; published in The Floyd County Times. Received at AFC in a folder with the heading: SGK's Prestonburg, KY. Visit.
  - "Library of Congress: Serious But Not Solemn," July 27, 1978 (Box-folder 11/9)
    Photocopy of a newspaper article by Clayton Jones in the Christian Science Monitor. Received at AFC in a folder with the heading: Library of Congress. box-folders 1/1, 8/6, 10/12, and 11/9 were formerly housed in one folder, but possibly not received in that grouping
  - Center for Southern Folklore brochures, 1978 (Box-folder 11/10)
    Promotional brochures mailed (in separate envelopes) to Knott and to Sandra Gatedevolt (the latter envelope is unopened). Sections from the Center for Southern Folklore Newsletter have been relocated to box-folder 12/20. Received at AFC in a folder with the heading: Southern Folklore Center-1978. This folder is with the current folder.
  - Center for Southern Folklore Newsletter, Vol. 1, No. 1, Spring 1978 (Box-folder 12/20)
    Copies of the newsletter; one has pen marks to indicate articles of note, and this copy also has an insert page of publicity for the Center for Southern Folklore collection. Relocated from box-folder 11/10.
  - Newspaper clippings, folder 1/2, circa 1940s (Box-folder 11/11)
    Multiple copies of original newspaper clippings. Received at AFC in a folder with the heading: Newspaper publicity/various papers and years/Please divide with Western [Western Kentucky University]. This folder is with the current folder.
  - Newspaper clippings, folder 2/2, circa 1940s (Box-folder 12/35)
    See the note for box-folder 11/11.
  - Newspaper clippings, 1976 (Box-folder 11/12)
    Photocopies of articles about the creation and physical locations of folk festivals. Received at AFC in a folder with the heading: Knott notes.
  - Newspaper clippings, undated (Box-folder 11/13)
    Photocopied newspaper clippings, from a later accrual.
- Series 9: Accruals
  - Accrual, circa 1946-1978 (Box-folder 11/14)
    Typed excerpt from the California Folklore Quarterly (January 1946), "Folk songs and Dances: The Changing Scene," by Knott, a photocopy of the folder and contents for "Folk Festivals and Folklore USA - new outline - 1975," correspondence, a copy of Free State Folklore (vol. III, no. 2; Winter 1976-1977), a photocopy of "Art and the Audience," a revised list of state arts councils (1970-1971), a photocopy of "Why a Folk Festival in United States," with a card stapled to it (with typed and handwritten notations), photocopied and original clippings, a copy of Folk Dance and Song Society News (no. 23; March 1978), a copy of the drawer and folder inventory of the collection at Western Kentucky University, plus a cover letter from Patricia MacLeish to Knott (April 21, 1978), a photocopy of "Many Songs, Many Dances" published in Américas, a handwritten list of resources at a public library, on the verso of 1937 National Folk Festival letterhead, a photocopy of the 1952 National Folk Festival "Notes and News" from the St. Louis Globe-Democrat, "Where Men Search for Peace" (a typed essay by Knott), "Religious Songs in the Kentucky Mountains" (a typed essay by Knott), and a photocopy (with some original pages) regarding the early days and plans for the National Folk Festival (with a cover letter from Knott to Joe Wilson, dated October 20, 1976). Received at AFC in a folder with the heading: (I) Book. The original folder was not retained. Materials in this folder pertaining to the acquisition of materials by Western Kentucky University and/or the Library of Congress were moved to the case folder.
  - Accrual, 1970s (Box-folder 11/15)
    Original and photocopied typed correspondence, typed essays, lists of National Folk Festival programs, a letter from Lynwood Montell to Joe Hickerson (in which he says Western Kentucky University has all of the National Folk Festival programs that Knott had)), an original copy of The Mountain Echo (newsletter of the Hindeman Settlement School; vol. 1, no. 1; November 1978), a copy of the National Folk Festival program (1978), newspaper clippings, a list of the National Folk Festival Board of Directors (1970), and other materials. Because this seems to be a gathering of some remaining papers for Knott to send to the Library of Congress, they have been retained as a unit rather than dispersed throughout the collection. The original folder, with Knott's name and address at 203 Nichols St., Princeton, Kentucky, was not retained.
  - Accrual (1/2), undated (Box-folder 11/16)
    Photocopies of clippings and documents. Oversized items have been relocated to box-folder 12/27.
  - Accrual (2/2), undated (Box-folder 12/27)
    Oversized photocopies of newspaper clippings and pages from various National Folk Festival administrative documents, which focus on diversity in festival participation. The folder also includes a photocopy of an original folder with the heading "North of the Border Knott" and with Knott's handwritten notes. Relocated from box-folder 11/16.
- Series 10: Photographs
  Most photo titles are taken from captions accompanying the photos. Titles for PH26-51 were created by the archivist.
  - Cherokee Indian square dancers; Cherokee, North Carolina, undated, AFC 1979/112: PH01; 1 photograph: black-and-white print; gelatin emulsion; 8 in. x 10 in. (Box-folder 11/17)
  - Israeli dancers from YMHA-YWHA, circa April 8, 1949, AFC 1979/112: PH02; 1 photograph: black-and-white print; gelatin emulsion; 8 in. x 10 in. (Box-folder 11/17)
  - Lloyd Shaw Dancers, Cheyenne Mountain School; Colorado Springs, Colorado, 1939 or 1940, AFC 1979/112: PH03; 1 photograph: black-and-white print; gelatin emulsion; 8 in. x 10 in. (Box-folder 11/17)
  - Canadian Folk Songs [sic] Singers, undated, AFC 1979/112: PH04; 1 photograph: black-and-white print; gelatin emulsion; 8 in. x 10 in. (Box-folder 11/17)
  - Howard Lowell, undated, AFC 1979/112: PH05; 1 photograph: black-and-white print; gelatin emulsion; 8 in. x 10 in. (Box-folder 11/17)
    French fiddler
  - Unidentified dancers, 1950, AFC 1979/112: PH06; 1 photograph: black-and-white print; gelatin emulsion; 8 in. x 10 in. (Box-folder 11/17)
  - Eddie Gallegos, New Mexican singer; Albuquerque, New Mexico, 1947, AFC 1979/112: PH07; 1 photograph: black-and-white print; gelatin emulsion; approx. 8 in. x 4 in. (Box-folder 11/17)
    This image is trimmed from a larger photo, not with the collection.
  - Dancers [Arab], Southern Illinois University, undated, AFC 1979/112: PH08; 1 photograph: black-and-white print; gelatin emulsion; 8 in. x 10 in. (Box-folder 11/17)
  - Santa Fe Fiesta - Maida Stark leading dance routine; Santa Fe, New Mexico, undated, AFC 1979/112: PH09; 1 photograph: black-and-white print; gelatin emulsion; 8 in. x 10 in. (Box-folder 11/17)
  - Mary Pickens, Charlene Dunn, Emma Guerra, Shirley Finch, Alice Mercer, Dorothy Fisdale, Lydia Perez - Spanish American folk dancers at the Santa Fe Fiesta, undated, AFC 1979/112: PH10; 1 photograph: black-and-white print; gelatin emulsion; 8 in. x 10 in. (Box-folder 11/17)
  - Rice Festival Dance, Philippine Embassy Dancers; Washington, D.C., April 7, 1949, AFC 1979/112: PH11; 1 photograph: black-and-white print; gelatin emulsion; approx. 8 in. x 6 in. (Box-folder 11/17)
  - Smooth and Clog - Appalachian Style - Canton, North Carolina, 1949, AFC 1979/112: PH12; 1 photograph: black-and-white print; gelatin emulsion; 8 in. x 10 in. (Box-folder 11/17)
  - Burl Ives - 100 Dollar Burl Ives Award for about 10 years for Social Singers and Musicians, circa 1955-1965, AFC 1979/112: PH13; 1 photograph: black-and-white print; gelatin emulsion; 8 in. x 10 in. (Box-folder 11/17)
  - "Friendly Four" (Acadian band), directed by fiddler James Grose; Mamon, Louisiana, possibly 1955, AFC 1979/112: PH14; 1 photograph: black-and-white print; gelatin emulsion; 8 in. x 10 in.; Accompanied by a copy negative; 4 3/4 in. x 4 in. (Box-folder 11/17)
  - Holland (Michigan) dance group at one of the National Folk Festivals, undated, AFC 1979/112: PH15; 1 photograph: black-and-white print; gelatin emulsion; 8 in. x 10 in.; Accompanied by a copy negative; 4 3/4 in. x 4 in. (Box-folder 11/17)
  - Czechoslovakians, Cleveland, Ohio, undated, AFC 1979/112: PH16; 1 photograph: black-and-white print; gelatin emulsion; 8 in. x 10 in.; Accompanied by a copy negative; 4 3/4 in. x 4 in. (Box-folder 11/17)
  - Ruth Tyler - "The Dulcimer Lady," Nieosho, Missouri, undated, AFC 1979/112: PH17; 1 photograph: black-and-white print; gelatin emulsion; 8 in. x 10 in.; Accompanied by a copy negative; 4 3/4 in. x 4 in. (Box-folder 11/17)
  - Singers of Shaker songs, undated, AFC 1979/112: PH18; 1 photograph: black-and-white print; gelatin emulsion; 8 in. x 10 in. (Box-folder 11/17)
  - Romanian ensemble (unconfirmed), undated, AFC 1979/112: PH19; 1 photograph: black-and-white print; gelatin emulsion; 8 in. x 10 in.; Accompanied by a copy negative; 4 3/4 in. x 4 in. (Box-folder 11/17)
  - Musicians in performance; banjoist and fiddler in front, undated, AFC 1979/112: PH20; 1 photograph: black-and-white print; gelatin emulsion; 8 in. x 10 in. (Box-folder 11/17)
  - French Canadian dancers, undated, AFC 1979/112: PH21; 1 photograph: black-and-white print; gelatin emulsion; 8 in. x 10 in. (Box-folder 11/17)
  - Hawaii Orchestra, undated, AFC 1979/112: PH22; 1 photograph: black-and-white print; gelatin emulsion; 8 in. x 10 in. (Box-folder 11/17)
  - Students who have been studying for two years making plans to come to the National Folk Festival in Washington, D.C., undated, AFC 1979/112: PH23; 1 photograph: black-and-white print; gelatin emulsion; 8 in. x 10 in. (Box-folder 11/17)
    Photographed on the campus of Maui College, on the island of Maui.
  - Old Spanish wedding, presented by students from Santa Cruz, New Mexico, High School, undated, AFC 1979/112: PH24; 1 photograph: black-and-white print; gelatin emulsion; 8 in. x 10 in. (Box-folder 11/17)
    Photographed in Kiel Auditorium, St. Louis, Missouri.
  - Texas guitarist-singer from West Virginia, undated, AFC 1979/112: PH25; 1 photograph: black-and-white print; gelatin emulsion; 8 in. x 10 in. (Box-folder 11/17)
  - Mrs. John T. McCay, director and founder of the Vancouver Folk Festival; British Columbia, Canada, undated, AFC 1979/112: PH26; 1 photograph: black-and-white print; gelatin emulsion; 8 in. x 10 in. (Box-folder 11/17)
    Also known as Nellie McCay or McKay.
  - National Folk Festival, June 30-July 4, 1972, AFC 1979/112: PH27-PH51; 25 photographs: black-and-white prints; 5 in. x 7 in. or smaller (Box-folder 11/17)
    Photos taken at the 1972 National Folk Festival. Images show musicians in performance, people socializing, etc. Gift from Sheryl Gilbert, 1973.